<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" xmlns:thr="http://purl.org/syndication/thread/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <title type="text">Today's Darling</title>
  <subtitle>Daily essays by Shigesato Itoi from 1101.com, translated to English.</subtitle>
  <updated>2026-01-31T20:50:19.179949+00:00</updated>
  <link href="https://www.1101.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
  <id>https://adtheriault.github.io/itoi-daily/feed.xml</id>
  <link href="https://adtheriault.github.io/itoi-daily/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <icon>https://adtheriault.github.io/itoi-daily/hobonichi%20logo.png</icon>
<entry>
    <id>https://adtheriault.github.io/itoi-daily/#f581b83f182b</id>
    <title>A Mother and Her Child.</title>
    <updated>2026-01-31T20:49:55.166728+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Shigesato Itoi</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 20px;"&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.1101.com/home/2025/images/home/darling.png" alt="Hobonichi Darling" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;"/&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;A friend's mother passed away,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and I read something they wrote about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was written not long after it happened,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and the words still seemed to hold body warmth—it made me cry a little.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, she might have been a stranger, but&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;there was something precious between mother and child there,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and though it might be sad,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found myself feeling envious too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A little earlier that day, I'd met with another friend,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and we talked about how among boys who'd done various "bad things,"&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the ones who had memories of being loved by "even just one person"&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;were more likely to turn their lives around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That one person, more often than not, was their mother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even hearing about that made me think "how nice"—&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn't help feeling a little envious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might seem strange for a full-grown adult, practically an old man,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;but what I love most of all&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;is watching mothers and children getting along well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look at my daughter and her daughter and think how wonderful it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to watch my boss at home with her mother&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;with that same kind of longing admiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I myself never had a relationship with my mother,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I spent a long time&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;practicing how to be "okay" with not having that relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But maybe as I've gotten older, I've become more honest—&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;"having a mother who loves you unconditionally"&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;is something I can now honestly see as a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A child being held tight by their mother, acting spoiled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could there be anything more blissful than that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don't have a single memory like that in my entire life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, no—I don't want people to feel sorry for me,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just want to give myself a little "you did well" pat on the back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I'm the only one saying it, that's more than enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mothers, children, those who love and are loved—&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to tell them: that's a wonderful "treasure" you have there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for visiting Hobonichi today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some reason today, I'm going to send this without reading it over. I'd just delete it anyway.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://www.1101.com/"/>
    <summary>A man reflects on his lifelong envy of mother-child bonds he never experienced, finding both pain and self-compassion in witnessing the unconditional love that shaped others but eluded him. With age, he's learned to honestly acknowledge this loss while giving himself the recognition he never received.</summary>
    <published>2026-01-31T20:49:55.166728+00:00</published>
  <media:thumbnail url="https://www.1101.com/home/2025/images/home/darling.png" width="200" height="200"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
