<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" xmlns:thr="http://purl.org/syndication/thread/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <title type="text">Today's Darling</title>
  <subtitle>Daily essays by Shigesato Itoi from 1101.com, translated to English.</subtitle>
  <updated>2026-01-31T11:47:07.881652+00:00</updated>
  <link href="https://www.1101.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
  <id>https://adtheriault.github.io/itoi-daily/feed.xml</id>
  <link href="https://adtheriault.github.io/itoi-daily/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <icon>https://adtheriault.github.io/itoi-daily/hobonichi%20logo.png</icon>
<entry>
    <id>https://adtheriault.github.io/itoi-daily/#5cb22a09388a</id>
    <title>The Person Called Mother, and Her Child.</title>
    <updated>2026-01-31T11:46:47.335298+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Shigesato Itoi</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 20px;"&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.1101.com/home/2025/images/home/darling.png" alt="Hobonichi Darling" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;"/&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;A friend's mother passed away, and I read something he wrote about it. He'd written it not long after it happened, and the words still seemed to carry body warmth—it made me cry a little. To me, she might have been a stranger, but there was something precious between mother and child captured there, and though it was a sad thing, I found myself feeling envious too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A little earlier that day, I'd been talking with another friend, and he told me about troubled boys who'd done all sorts of "bad things"—but the ones who had memories of being "loved by even just one person" were more likely to turn their lives around. Usually, he said, that person was their mother. Hearing that, I couldn't help but think "how nice" and feel a little envious again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might seem strange for a grown man—an old man, even—but there's nothing I love more than watching mothers and children getting along well together. I look at my daughter and her daughter and think how wonderful it is. I used to watch my boss and his mother with that same kind of longing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it's because I never had that relationship with my own mother—I spent so many years practicing how to be "fine" with that absence. But as I've gotten older, maybe I've become more honest with myself. I can now genuinely think how good it must be to "have a mother who loves you unconditionally." A child being held tight by their mother, acting spoiled—is there any greater happiness than that? I don't have a single memory like that in my entire life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, no—I don't want anyone to feel sorry for me. I just want to give myself a little pat and say "you did well." That's all I need—just me saying it to myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mothers, children, those who love and are loved—what a wonderful treasure that is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for coming to "Hobo Nikkan" today. I'm going to send this without reading it over. Otherwise I'll just delete it.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <link href="https://www.1101.com/"/>
    <summary>A man reflects on his lifelong envy of mother-child bonds he observes around him, honestly acknowledging the absence of maternal love in his own life while finding peace in simply telling himself "you did well."</summary>
    <published>2026-01-31T11:46:47.335298+00:00</published>
  <media:thumbnail url="https://www.1101.com/home/2025/images/home/darling.png" width="200" height="200"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
